Paul Henry Sheats Papers
Paul Henry Sheats Papers
1925-1975
Sheats, Paul H., 1907-
54 linear ft.
Files of the American educator (1907-1984). Personal files include oral history, correspondence from and about Theodor Wilhelm, memorabilia, photographs, material on Nazi education, student papers, speeches, selected writings, some audio-visual material, etc. There are organizational records for several California education organizations as well as a number of key national adult education organizations including the Adult Education Association of the U.S.A., Association of University Evening Colleges, Center for the Study of Liberal Education for Adults, National Association of State Universities and Land-Grant Colleges, National University Extension Association, UNESCO, and University Council on Education for Public Responsibility. There are also more than 40 subject and country files and information on meetings and conferences, and two audiorecordings.
149580
Biographical History
Born on December 5, 1907 in Tiffin, Ohio, Paul Sheats (1907-1984) attended Heidelberg College in his hometown where he earned his A.B. in 1929. He went on to earn an M.A. from Columbia University in 1930, and a Ph.D. from Yale University in 1936. He was an instructor in government at New York State College for Teachers in Albany, an instructor in education at Yale, and an assistant professor of education at the University of Wisconsin. During World War II he served for a time as head of the adult section of the Office of War Information. Sheats has also been the education director of Town Hall in New York. In 1946 he joined the University of California as Associate Director of Extension and in 1949 he became a full professor, a position he held until his retirement in 1975. In 1957 he became Director of University Extension and was named Dean of Extension in 1958. He held this position until 1967 when he returned to teaching full-time. He was also a professor of education at University of California, Los Angeles.
In the course of his life he maintained memberships with several key adult education organizations. Sheats was President of both the National University Extension Association and the Adult Education Association. He served as the University Extension representative on the Executive Committee of the National Association of State Universities and Land-Grant Colleges. He also served on the Board of Directors of the National Training Laboratories and on the Adult Education Committee of the Master Plan Survey Team, which acted as architects for the Master Plan for Higher Education in California. For six years Dr. Sheats served on the UNESCO National Commission (at one time holding the office of Vice-Chairman), and he was a member of President Kennedy's Panel of Consultants on Vocational Education. In addition he held seats on the Boards of Directors for the Center for the Study of Liberal Education for Adults and the National Training Laboratories.
Paul Sheats' articles appeared in the major adult education publications, and he authored or co-authored a number of books including Citizenship Throuqh the Social Studies (with R. W. Frederick), 1936; Forums for Young People (with J. W. Studebaker and C. S. Williams), 1937; Education and the Quest for a Middle Way, 1938; Forums on the Air, 1939; Adult education: the community approach, 1953; Adult Education (with R. Spence and C. Jayne), 1953; University of California Extension in a decade of transition, 1962; The case against the adult dropout, 1965; and Aging and the imagination, 1976.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Paul Henry Sheats Papers are divided into seven series.
The papers in Personal files pertain to Paul Sheats, the person. The files begin with biographical information in the form of a transcript of an oral history. Correspondence, memorabilia and photographs follow. Next are files devoted to Sheats's activities and interests from the 1930s through the 1960s. Of note are the files for Nazi educational philosophy, public forums and university extension. The files continue with copies of speeches, interviews and reports authored by Sheats from 1946-1970. There are files with some of Sheats's writings, however, they are selective; five writing projects undertaken in the late 1960s and 1970, as well as four books which he authored and a doctoral dissertation by his wife, June Barth Dow. The personal files conclude with audio visual material such as slides and tapes.
Organizational records consists of files for organizations with which Sheats was affiliated. The organizations, appearing alphabetically in the files, are:
Adult Education Association, 1961-1966 (includes material from the Special Conference on the War on Poverty, 1964)
American Council on Education, 1963-1964
Association of University Evening Colleges, 1953-1968
California State Board of Education - Advisory Committee on Adult Education, 1967-1970
Center for the Study of Liberal Education for Adults, 1953-1969 (includes a history of the CSLEA by James B. Whipple)
International Community College, 1970-1972
National Association of State Universities and Land-Grant Colleges, 1958-1967 (The 1961 meeting is of special interest because it was the centennial of the Morrill Land-Grant Act. Sheats served as chairman of the organization's Division of Extension.)
National Training Laboratories, 1947-1970
National University Extension Association, 1949-1970
Southern Regional Education Board - Adult Basic Education - Staff Development Project - Southeastern Region, 1969-1973
Unesco, 1951-1974
University Council on Education for Public Responsibility, 1962-1963
University of California Extension, 1958-1967
University of California, Los Angeles, 1971-1974
Western Training Laboratory, 1952-1969
Youth Opportunity Board of Greater Los Angeles, 1965
Paul Sheats attended over 70 meetings and conferences of note for which he kept records which comprise Meetings files. The meetings are arranged in alphabetical order by sponsor. Many adult education associations and universities are represented in these files.
During the course of 50 years, Sheats collected information about various components of adult education. He kept Subject files as a means for easy organization, containment, and access of this information. The collection has preserved this order, maintaining the same subject headings used by Sheats. Topics range from adult basic education to consumer education, from labor education to World War II. Topics have been subdivided if the bulk and nature of the material warranted such a division. Arrangement of the subject files is alphabetical.
The Geographical files are similar in nature to the subject files. Material about education from around the world is grouped primarily by country, however, some material is designated by geographic region. Countries represented here range from Africa to Yugoslavia.
The Printed material files are the most ambiguous division within the collection. This division was not used by Paul Sheats in his filing system, however, these materials could not readily be integrated within the existing framework of the collection. The material is filed alphabetically under author or title.
Recordings contains two LPs, each with two episode of an educational radio show.
Arrangement of the Collection
The inventory reflects the intellectual organization of the material and gathers related material under the same heading(s), but because the material arrived in two distinct accessions separated by many years, material for a given topic may be physically located in more than one place. For this same reason, the organizational files from the two accessions are arranged slightly differently. The researcher will be well advised to review the entire inventory carefully to ensure that no relevant material is missed.
Related Material
The library holds a considerable number of collections related to adult and continuing education. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Adult education; Sheats, Paul H., 1907-; Wilhelm, Theodor, 1906-; American Association for Adult and Continuing Education.; American Council on Education.; Association of State Universities and Land-Grant Colleges.; Association of University Evening Colleges (U.S.); California State Board of Education, Advisory Committee on Adult Education.; Center for the Study of Liberal Education for Adults.; International Community College.; National University Extension Association.; NTL Institute for Applied Behavioral Science.; Southern Regional Education Board, Adult Basic Education, Staff Development Project, Southeastern Region.; U.S. National Commission for UNESCO.; University Council on Education for Public Responsibility.; University of California (System), University Extension.; University of California, Los Angeles.; Western Training Laboratory, World Confederation of Organizations of the Teaching Profession.; Youth Opportunity Board of Greater Los Angeles.; Adult education -- Study and teaching.; Adult education -- Africa.; Adult education -- Australia.; Adult education -- Canada.; Adult education -- Europe.; Adult education -- Great Britain.; Adult education -- India.; Adult education -- Methodology.; Adult education -- New Zealand.; Adult education -- Research.; Adult education -- United States.; Adult education teachers -- Training of.; Older people -- United States.; Apartheid -- South Africa.; Basic education.; Community development -- United States.; Community education -- United States.; Education -- 1945-1964.; Education -- 1965-; Educators -- United States.; Evening and continuation schools -- United States.; Evening and continuation schools -- California.; Literacy.; Mass media in education.; National socialism and education.; University extension -- United States.; Vocational education -- United States.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Pamphlets.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Education and the war.; Abstracts (summaries); Annual reports.; Sound recordings.; Awards.; Bibliographies.; Correspondence.; Drafts (documents); Memorabilia.; Memorandums.; Minutes (administrative records); Newsletters.; Notes (documents); Oral histories (document genres); Pamphlets.; Press releases.; Proceedings.; Reports.; Slides (photographs); Speeches (documents); School yearbooks.; Educators.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Paul H. Sheats, 1968, 1985
Inventory
- Personal files
  - Biographical
    - Oral History (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - Dr. Theodor Wilhelm, 1936-1939 (Box 1)
      See also European trip; Nazi educational philosophy
    - Australia, 1959-1960 (Box 1)
    - Sabbatical, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Memorabilia
    - Yearbooks
      - Columbian High School, Tiffin, Ohio, 1925 (Box 1)
      - Heidelberg College, Tiffin, Ohio, 1929 (Box 1)
      - New York State College for Teachers, Albany, NY, 1931 (Box 1)
    - Awards
      - Delbert Clark Award in Adult Education, 23 May 1970 (Box 2)
      - Adult Education Association of the U.S.A., President, 1953-1954 (Box 97)
      - Adult Educators of Greater Los Angeles, May 1975 (Box 97)
      - National University Extension Association, Julius M. Nolte Award, 29 Apr 1975 (Box 97)
  - Photographs
    - Debate Club, Tiffin, Ohio High School, 1924 (Box 2)
    - Reception for President Johnson at UCLA, February 21, 1964 (Box 2)
    - Vocational Education Panel at the White House, November 27, 1962 (Box 2)
  - European trip records, 1935 (Box 2)
    See also Dr. Theodor Wilhelm; Nazi educational philosophy
  - Nazi educational philosophy, 1930s (Box 2)
    See also Dr. Theodor Wilhelm; European trip records
  - Public forums
    - Personal File, 1930s-1940s (Box 2)
    - Counseling, 1930s-1940s (Box 2)
    - Publications, 1930s-1940s; 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Publicity, 1930s (Box 2)
    - Reporting Projects, 1930s (Box 2)
    - Scheduling, 1930s (Box 2)
    - Short Programs, 1930s-1940s (Box 3)
    - Subjects and References, 1930s (Box 3)
    - Chattanooga, Hamilton County Public Forum Scrapbook, 1936-1937; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Town Hall
      - Lecture Division, 1940s (Box 3)
      - Workshop Division, 1940s (Box 3)
    - American Platform Guild, 1940s (Box 3)
    - National Education Association, 1940s (Box 3)
    - New Tools for Learning, 1940s (Box 3)
    - University of Wisconsin, 1930s-1940s (Box 4)
    - Metropolitan Youth Council, 1940s (Box 4)
    - Office of War Information, 1940s (Box 4)
  - University Extension
    - Reorganization, 1964-1965; 1967-1968 (Box 4)
    - Resignation, 1967 (Box 4)
      See also Organizational records: University of California Extension
  - Student papers
    - Issues in Adult Education, 232B, 1971 (Box 4)
    - Seminar on Research in Adult, Vocational, and Technical Education, 261G, 1969
  - University of Lethbridge Consultation, 1967-1968 (Box 4)
    See also Geographical files: Canada: University of Lethbridge
  - Speeches, interviews, etc.
    - Table of Contents, v. 1 and v. 2, 1946-1947 (Box 4)
    - Volume 1, no's 1-33. 35-41 (Box 4)
    - Volume 2, no. 42-66 (Box 5)
  - Speeches, forms and reports
    - Indices, v. 1-5, 1954-1966 (Box 5)
    - v. 1, no. 1-38 (Box 5)
    - v. 2, no. 39-80 (Box 5)
    - v. 3, no. 80a-155, 158-165 (Box 6)
    - v. 4, no. 166-185 (Box 6)
    - v. 5, no. 186-208 (Box 6)
    - [Miscellaneous], 1961; 1967-1968,; 1970 (Box 6)
  - Writings
    - Administration of Adult Basic Education
      - Outline (Box 7)
      - Draft, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Encyclopedia of Education, "Continuing Education" (field article)
      - Correspondence, 1967-1969 (Box 7)
      - Outline and article, 1969 (Box 7)
    - Foundation of Education, Chapter 27 - Learning Society, 1970
      - Drafts, 3 folders (Box 7)
      - Proof (Box 7)
      - Teacher's Manual draft (Box 7)
    - Handbook of Adult Education in the U.S. - Introduction, 1970
      - Handwritten copy (Box 7)
      - Draft (Box 7)
      - Rough final draft (Box 7)
      - Final Draft (Box 7)
      - Master copy (Box 7)
    - We Keep on Learning: The Growth of Adult Education in America
      - Correspondence, 1961; 1966 (Box 7)
      - Draft, 1966 (Box 7)
    - Published works
      - Adult Education: The Community Approach, by Paul H. Sheats, 1953; 1 volume (Box 98)
      - Citizenship Education Through the Social Studies: A Philosophy and a Program by Robert Wendell Frederick, 1936; 1 volume (Box 98)
      - Education and the Quest for a Middle Way, by Paul H. Sheats, 1938; 1 volume (Box 98)
      - Handbook of Adult Education in the U.S., by Malcolm S. Knowles, 1960; 1 volume (Box 98)
    - Dissertation
      - Characteristics of Noncredit University Extension Students, by June Barth Dow, 1965; includes four loose sheets of typescript which appear to be part of an interview or conversation between Sheats and Dow, numbered 221 through 223; 1 volume (Box 98)
  - Audio-visual materials
    - Records
      - The People Act, Programs 9 and 10 (Box 96)
      - The Ways of Mankind, Program 7 and 8 (Box 96)
    - Slides
      - Dr. Sheats, 1973 (Box 96)
    - Tapes
      - Unesco (4), 1 audiocassette (Box 96)
      - Aldous Huxley (2), 2 reel-to-reel audiotapes (Box 96)
      - Illich, 1 reel-to-reel audiotape (Box 96)
      - Frank Jessup/UCLA Seminar, 1 reel-to-reel audiotape (Box 96)
      - Learning to Be, 1 videotape (Box 96)
      - Miscellaneous (2), 2 videotapes (Box 96)
- Organizational records
  - Adult Education Association
    - Annual conference, 1961 (Box 99)
    - Annual conference, 1963 (Box 99)
    - Special conference, 1961 (Box 99)
    - Special conference (on War on Poverty), 1964 (Box 99)
    - National Conference, 1965 (Box 99)
    - Report on Current Business, 1966 (Box 99)
  - American Council on Education
    - Annual meeting, 1963 (Box 99)
    - Annual meeting, 1964 (Box 99)
  - Association of University Evening Colleges
    - Annual meetings, See Meetings, below.
    - Committee on Minimum Data and Definitions, 1960-1966; reports (Box 7)
    - Committee on Relationships with Other Organizations, 1963 (Box 100)
    - Research Committee, 1959 (Box 7)
    - Meetings
      Material is split between boxes 7, 8, 9, 99 and 100.
      - 15th Annual, 1953 (Box 7)
      - 18th Annual, 1956 (Box 7)
      - 19th Annual, 1957 (Box 7)
      - 20th Annual, 1958 (Box 8)
      - 21st Annual, 1959 (Box 8)
      - 22nd Annual, 1960 (Box 8)
      - [22d] Annual meeting, 1960; organizational correspondence and general plans (Box 99)
      - [22d] Annual meeting, 1960; reports and notes (Box 99)
      - 23rd Annual, 1961 (Box 8)
      - [23d] Annual meeting, 1961 (Box 99)
      - 24th Annual, 1962 (Box 8)
      - 25th Annual, 1963 (Box 8)
      - 26th Annual, 1964 (Box 9)
      - [26th] Annual meeting, 1964 (Box 99)
      - 27th Annual, 1965 (Box 9)
      - [27th] Annual meeting, 1965 (Box 99)
      - 28th Annual, 1966 (Box 9)
      - [28th] Annual meeting, 1966
        - Organizational correspondence and general plans (Box 99)
        - Address and notes by Paul H. Sheats (Box 99)
        - Reports and notes (Box 99)
      - [29th] Annual meeting, 1967 (Box 100)
    - Printed materials
      - "From the Dean's Desk...", 1965; 1969 (Box 9)
      - Newsletters, 1955-1963; v. 3, no. 4; v. 4, no. 1, 3; v. 5, no. 7, 8; v. 6, no. 2, 6-8; v. 7, no. 1-8; v. 8, no. 1-8; v. 9, no. 1-8; v. 10, no. 1-8; v. 11, no. 1-8; 6 folders
      - Newsletters, 1963-1968; v. 12, no. 1-8; v. 13, no. 1-7; v. 14, no. 1-6; v. 15, no. 1-6; v. 16, no. 3-6; 5 folders (Box 10)
      - Who's Who in 1964 (Box 10)
  - California State Board of Education. Advisory Committee on Adult Education
    - Correspondence, 1967-1970 (Box 10)
    - Meetings
      - [General], 1968 (Box 10)
      - Conference, 1970 (Box 10)
    - Surveys, 1968-1969 (Box 10)
    - Administrative and Operational Concerns Task Force, 1969-1970 (Box 10)
    - Curriculum Task Force, 1970 (Box 10)
    - Finance and Facilities Task Force, 1969-1970 (Box 10)
    - Personnel Task Force, 1969-1970 (Box 10)
    - Students Task Force, 1969-1970 (Box 10)
  - Center for the Study of Liberal Education for Adults
    - Annual Leadership Conference, 1965 (Box 100)
    - Carnegie Corporation - Commonwealth Fund, 1967 (Box 11)
    - Ford Foundation grants, 1962 (Box 11)
    - History, 1967 (Box 11)
    - Interim reports, 6th and 7th, Oct 1953 - Sep 1954; Oct 1955 (Box 11)
    - Liberal education, 1955 (Box 11)
    - University Extension, 1962 (Box 11)
    - Speeches by John B. Schwertman, Director, 1954-1955 (Box 11)
    - Meetings
      - Board of Directors, 10-11 Mar 1962 (Box 11)
      - Board of Directors, 12 Mar 1964 (Box 11)
      - Board of Directors, 1966 (Box 100)
      - Board of Directors, Oct 1966; workikng papers; 2 folders (Box 100)
      - Board of Directors, 1967 (Box 100)
      - Board of Directors, 20 Mar 1967 (Box 11)
      - Board of Directors, 15-16 Sep 1967 (Box 11)
      - Conference of Liberal Arts Deans, 1954 (Box 11)
      - 4th Leadership Conference for University Adult Educators, 1956 (Box 11)
      - National Conference on the Urban University and Community Needs, 1954 (Box 12)
    - Printed materials
      - CSLEA Reports, 1961-1968; 4 folders (Box 12)
      - Continuing Education for Adults, 1961-1973; 4 folders (Box 12)
      - Notes and Essays on Education for Adults, 1952-1962; no. 1, 2, 4-11, 13-31, 34-36; 6 folders (Box 13)
      - Notes and Essays on Education for Adults, 1963-1969; no. 37-55, 57-59; 5 folders (Box 14)
      - Occasional Papers, 1960s; no. 1, 2, 4-13, 15-17; 2 folders (Box 15)
      - Reports, 1955; 1957-1958,; 1960-1961; 2 folders (Box 15)
      - Research Reports, 1961; 1963-1964,; 1968; 3 folders (Box 15)
      - Reports, 1953; 1957-1959 (Box 16)
      - Reprints, 1956; 1957,; 1959 (Box 16)
  - International Community College
    - Board of Governors
      - Correspondence, 1970-1972 (Box 16)
      - Meetings, 1971-1972 (Box 16)
      - Catalogs, 1971-1972 (Box 16)
    - Printed materials, miscellaneous, circa 1970s (Box 16)
  - National Association of State Universities and Land-Grant Colleges
    - Annual meeting
      - 72nd Annual, 1958 (Box 16)
      - 72nd Annual (cont.), 1958 (Box 100)
      - 73rd Annual, 1959 (Box 16)
      - 74th Annual, 1960 (Box 16)
      - 74th Annual (cont.), 1960 (Box 100)
      - 75th Annual, 1961
        - v. 1 and 2 (Box 17)
        - Organizational correspondence, Dec 1960-Nov 1961; 2 folders (Box 100)
        - General plans (Box 100)
        - Press releases (Box 101)
        - Addresses (Box 101)
        - Reports, 2 folders (Box 101)
      - 77th Annual, 1963
        - Organizational correspondence (Box 101)
        - General plans (Box 101)
        - Reports, 2 folders (Box 101)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 17)
      - 78th Annual, 1964
        - Organizational correspondence (Box 101)
        - General plans (Box 101)
        - Addresses and notes (Box 101)
        - Reports, 2 folders (Box 101)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 17)
      - 79th Annual, 1965
        - Organizational correspondence (Box 102)
        - General plans (Box 102)
        - Addresses (Box 102)
        - Reports and resolutions (Box 102)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 17)
      - 80th Annual, 1966
        - Organizational correspondence and general plans (Box 102)
        - Addresses (Box 102)
      - 81st Annual, 1967 (Box 17)
    - Executive Committee Meetings, 1964-1966 May; 8 folders (Box 102)
    - Executive Committee Meetings, 1966, Sep (Box 103)
    - Division of Extension Meetings, 1964; 1966; 2 folders (Box 103)
    - Centennial Committee, 1960-1962
      - General plans and organizational correspondence (Box 103)
      - Publications (Box 103)
      - News articles (Box 103)
      - Extension questionnaire (Box 103)
      - Citizen Seminars (Box 103)
    - Ad Hoc Committee on Membership Meeting, Jul 1966 (Box 103)
    - Questionnaire on Administrative Problems and Practices, 1963 (Box 103)
    - Newsletter, 1963-1966; 3 folders (Box 103)
    - Task Force on the State University and Public Affairs, 1964-1967 (Box 16)
  - National Training Laboratories
    - College Leaders, 2d, 1961 (Box 17)
    - Committee on Minority Group Affairs / Negotiating, Committee of Black Ad Hoc Committee, 6 Sep 1969; minutes (Box 17)
    - Community Leadership Training, 2d, 1961 (Box 17)
    - Community Leadership Training Reading Book, 1969 (Box 18)
    - Conference on Executive Behavior and Organizational Effectiveness, 1961 (Box 18)
    - Group Development [meetings]
      - 1st, 1947 (Box 18)
      - 2nd, 1948 (Box 18)
      - 3d, 1949 (Box 18)
      - 4th, 1950 (Box 18)
      - 4th (cont.), 1950 (Box 19)
      - 5th, 1951 (Box 19)
      - Reports, 1951 (Box 19)
      - 1st Session, 1951 (Box 19)
      - 2nd Session, 1951 (Box 20)
      - 6th, 1952 (Box 20)
      - 7th, 1953 (Box 20)
      - Master file, 1953 (Box 20)
      - Bulletins, 1948; 1951,; 1955; no. 2-4, 6; 2 folders (Box 21)
      - Explorations in Human Relations Training: An Assessment of Experience, 1947-1953 (Box 21)
    - Executive Committee Meeting, Mar 1963 (Box 104)
    - Human Relations Training
      - 15th, 1961 (Box 21)
      - 17th, 1963 (Box 21)
      - Applications, no. 1-3, 1966 (Box 21)
      - Explorations, no. 2, 1966 (Box 21)
      - News, 1963-1968; v. 7, no. 4; v. 9, no. 4; v. 10, no. 2-4; v. 11, no. 2-3, Index; v. 12, no. 4 (Box 21)
      - Reading Book, Rev., 1969 (Box 21)
    - Leadership Skills Workshop for Elementary School Principals, 1st, 1958 (Box 21)
    - Management Work Conference, 7th, 1961-1962 (Box 22)
    - National Board Meetings, 1961-1963; 5 folders (Box 104)
    - NTL for Educators, 3d, 1961 (Box 22)
    - Protestant Church Leadership Laboratory, 6th, 1961 (Box 22)